I think the beautiful Malin [Akerman] put it perfectly.
أعتقد أن مالين (أكرمان ) اللطيف صاغها بالطريقة المثلى
Every man deserves the opportunity
كل رجل يستحق الفرصة
to grow a little bit of luxury.
للحصول على القليل من الرفاهية
Ladies and gentlemen, and more importantly,
سيداتي ساداتي ، والأهم من ذلك
Mo Bros and Mo Sistas — (Laughter) —
إخواني -الشوارب -و أخوتي - الشوارب -(ضحك)
for the next 17 minutes, I'm going to share with you
خلال ال 17 دقيقة القادمة، سأشارككم
my Movember journey, and how, through that journey,
رحلتي في موفمبر، وكيف أنه خلال هذه الرحلة ،
we've redefined charity, we're redefining the way
أعدنا صياغة معنى العمل الخيري، أعدنا صياغة الطريقة
prostate cancer researchers are working together
التي يتعامل بها باحثوا سرطان البروستات مع بعضهم البعض
throughout the world, and I hope, through that process,
في أنحاء العالم ، و أنا أتمنى ، من خلال هذه العملية ،
that I inspire you to create something significant
أستطيع إلهامكم كي توجدوا أمر قيم
in your life, something significant that will go on
في حياتكم، أمر قيم يمتد
and make this world a better place.
ليجعل من هذا العالم مكان أفضل
So the most common question I get asked,
إذن ، السؤال الذي يتكرر طرحه علي دوما ،
and I'm going to answer it now so I don't have to do it
والذي سأجيب عليه الآن حتى لا أضطر للقيام به
over drinks tonight, is how did this come about?
أثناء الشرب لاحقا الليلة، هو كيف أتتك الفكرة؟
How did Movember start?
كيف بدأ موفمبر؟
Well, normally, a charity starts with the cause, and someone
حسنا، تبدأ المؤسسة الخيرية عادة بقضية محددة و بشخص
that is directly affected by a cause.
متضرر مباشرة من هذه القضية
They then go on to create an event, and beyond that,
ثم يتطور الأمر لترتيب حدث، وفوق هذا
a foundation to support that.
إيجاد مؤسسة لدعم الحدث
Pretty much in every case, that's how a charity starts.
في الأغلب ، هذه هي طريقة إنشاء مؤسسة خيرية
Not so with Movember. Movember started in a very
لكن ليس هذا الحال مع موفمبر، فموفمبر إبتدأت
traditional Australian way. It was on a Sunday afternoon.
بطريقة إسترالية تقليدية جدا ، بدايتها كانت بعد ظهيرة يوم الأحد
I was with my brother and a mate having a few beers,
كنت مع اخي وصديقي نشرب البيرة
and I was watching the world go by,
وكنت أرى الناس يمرون من حولي
had a few more beers, and the conversation turned
تناولت بعض كؤوس البيرة، وهنا تحول الحديث
to '70s fashion — (Laughter) —
إلى موضة السبعينات - (ضحك)
and how everything manages to come back into style.
وكيف أن السبعينات عادت إلى الموضة اليوم
And a few more beers, I said, "There has to be some stuff
تناولت عدة كؤوس بيرة ، ثم قلت :" يجب أن يكون هناك أشياء
that hasn't come back." (Laughter)
لم تعد بعد " (ضحك)
Then one more beer and it was, whatever happened to the mustache?
بعد كأس بيرة آخر، قلت مالذي حدث للشارب ؟
Why hasn't that made a comeback? (Laughter)
لماذا لم يعد مع الموضة؟( ضحك)
So then there was a lot more beers, and then the day ended
بعدها شربت الكثير من البيرة ، وانتهى اليوم
with a challenge to bring the mustache back. (Laughter)
بتحدي إعادة الشارب إلى الموضة مرة أخرى ( ضحك)
So in Australia, "mo" is slang for mustache,
إذن في أستراليا (mo) هي كلمة عامية للشارب
so we renamed the month of November "Movember"
لذا قمنا بإعادة تسمية شهر نوفمبر ب (موفمبر)
and created some pretty basic rules, which still stand today.
وقمنا بإعداد عدة قواعد أساسية ،و التي لازالت قائمة حتى اليوم
And they are: start the month clean-shaven,
وهي : إبدأ الشهر حليق الذقن
rock a mustache -- not a beard, not a goatee, a mustache --
أطلق شاربك -- ليس لحيتك ، ولا حتى لحية الماعز، إنما شارب
for the 30 days of November, and then we agreed
طوال ال30 يوم من شهر نوفمبر ، واتفقنا أنه بعد ذلك
that we would come together at the end of the month,
أن نجتمع في نهاية الشهر ،
have a mustache-themed party, and award a prize
نقوم بإعداد حفلة فكرتها الرئيسية الشارب ، ونعد جائزة
for the best, and of course, the worst mustache. (Laughter)
لأفضل شارب ، وبالطبع ، أسوء شارب (ضحك)
Now trust me, when you're growing a mustache
الآن صدقوني، عندما تقوم بإطلاق شارب
back in 2003, and there were 30 of us back then,
في ذلك الوقت عام 2003، ولقد كنا 30 شخص آنذاك ،
and this was before the ironic hipster mustache movement
كان ذلك قبل أن أن تبدأ الحركة الساخرة لمحبي الشوارب
— (Laughter) —
-(ضحك)-
it created a lot of controversy. (Laughter)
لقد خلفت الكثير من الجدل .(ضحك)
So my boss wouldn't let me go and see clients.
فلم يكن يسمح لي مديري بمقابلة الزبائن .
My girlfriend at the time, who's no longer my girlfriend — (Laughter) — hated it.
صديقتي في ذلك الوقت، والتي لم تعد صديقتي الآن - (ضحك) - كرهت شاربي
Parents would shuffle kids away from us. (Laughter)
تجد الآباء يبعدون أبنائهم عن طريقنا . (ضحك)
But we came together at the end of the month and
ولكننا كنا نجتمع في نهاية الشهر و
we celebrated our journey, and it was a real journey.
نحتفل برحلتنا ، و التي كانت رحلة حقيقة.
And we had a lot of fun, and in 2004, I said to the guys,
لقد استمتعنا حقا، وفي عام 2004 ، قلت لأصدقائي
"That was so much fun. We need to legitimize this
" إنه شيء ممتع جدا. يجب أن نجعله قانوني
so we can get away with it year on year." (Laughter)
حتى نستطيع أن نقوم به سنة تلو الأخرى" (ضحك)
So we started thinking about that, and we were inspired
فبدأنا بالتفكير في الأمر ، وألهمنا
by the women around us and all they were doing for breast cancer.
بالنساء من حولنا وما يقدمونه لمرض سرطان الثدي
And we thought, you know what, there's nothing for men's health.
عندها فكرنا، بأنه لا يوجد أي شيء لدعم صحة الرجل
Why is that? Why can't we combine growing a mustache
لماذا؟ لما لا نقوم بربط تربية الشارب
and doing something for men's health?
بشيء نقدمه لصحة الرجل ؟
And I started to research that topic, and discovered
فبدأت بالبحث في الموضوع، واكتشفت
prostate cancer is the male equivalent of breast cancer
بأن سرطان البروستات هو المقابل لسرطان الثدي
in terms of the number of men that die from it and are diagnosed with it.
بناء على عدد الرجال الذين يشّخصون ويموتون بسببه
But there was nothing for this cause,
لكنني لم أجد أي شيء لهذه القضية،
so we married growing a mustache with prostate cancer,
لذلك قمنا بقرن تربية الشارب مع سرطان البروستات،
and then we created our tagline, which is,
عندها قمنا بتكوين شعارنا ، وهو
"Changing the face of men's health."
" تغيير وجه الإهتمام بصحة الرجل "
And that eloquently describes the challenge,
ولقد عبر ذلك ببلاغة عن التحدي ،
changing your appearance for the 30 days,
تغيير مظهرك لمدة 30 يوم ،
and also the outcome that we're trying to achieve:
بالإضافة إلى النتيجة التي نحاول تحقيقها:
getting men engaged in their health, having them have
العمل على توعية الرجال بصحتهم ، وذلك عن طريق
a better understanding about the health risks that they face.
توعيتهم بالمخاطر الصحية التي يواجهوها
So with that model, I then
بهذا النموذج ، قمت
cold-called the CEO of the Prostate Cancer Foundation.
بمحادثة كبير الإداريين التنفيذيين في مؤسسة سرطان البروستات
I said to him, "I've got the most amazing idea
قلت له : " لدي فكرة رائعة جدا
that's going to transform your organization." (Laughter)
والتي ستكون بمثابة نقلة لمؤسستك" (ضحك)
And I didn't want to share with him the idea over the phone,
ولم أرغب بمشاركته الفكرة عبر الهاتف ،
so I convinced him to meet with me for coffee in Melbourne
فقمت بإقناعه بلقائي في ملبورن لشرب القهوة،
in 2004.
في عام 2004
And we sat down, and I shared with him my vision
جلسنا سويا وشاركته رؤيتي
of getting men growing mustaches across Australia,
في تريبة الرجال ،في جميع أنحاء أستراليا، لشواربهم
raising awareness for this cause,
وذلك لرفع مستوى التوعية بهذه القضية
and funds for his organization. And I needed a partnership
وجمع التبرعات لمؤسسته. و أنني بحاجة إلى شريك
to legitimately do that.
حتى أستطيع القيام بذلك بشكل قانوني وشرعي .
And I said, "We're going to come together at the end,
و قلت :" سنقوم جميعا بالإجتماع في نهاية الشهر ،
we're going to have a mustache-themed party, we're going to have DJs,
سنقوم بتنظيم حفلة فكرتها مبنية على الشارب ، بوجود دي جي
we're going to celebrate life, and we're going to change the face of men's health."
سنحتفل بالحياة، وسنقوم بتغيير وجه صحة الرجل"
And he just looked at me and laughed, and he said,
نظر إلي ، ضحك وقال
he said, "Adam, that's a really novel idea,
قال :" آدم ، إنها فكرة جديدة حقا ،
but we're an ultraconservative organization.
ولكننا مؤسسة محافظة متشددة
We can't have anything to do with you." (Laughter)
ولا نستطيع التعاون معك " (ضحك)
So I paid for coffee that day — (Laughter) —
بالتالي قمت بدفع ثمن القهوة ذلك اليوم - (ضحك)
and his parting comment as we shook hands was,
وعند الوداع أثناء تصافحنا علق قائلا:
"Listen, if you happen to raise any money out of this,
" اسمع ، إن استطعت جمع أية مال من هذه الفكرة ،
we'll gladly take it." (Laughter)
سيسرنا إستقباله" (ضحك)
So my lesson that year was persistence.
بذلك كان الدرس الذي تعلمته تلك السنة هو الإصرار
And we persisted, and we got 450 guys
ولقد أصررنا ، وقمنا بجمع 450 رجل
growing mustaches, and together we raised 54,000 dollars,
قاموا بتربية شواربهم ، وقمنا سويا بجمع 54.000 دولار
and we donated every cent of that to the Prostate Cancer Foundation of Australia,
وقمنا بالتبرع بكل سنت من هذا المال إلى مؤسسة سرطان البروستات بأستراليا
and that represented at the time the single biggest donation
في ذلك الوقت ، هذا المبلغ كان أكبر مبلغ من مصدر متبرع واحد
they'd ever received.
حصلت عليه المؤسسة
So from that day forward, my life has become about a mustache.
منذ ذلك الوقت ، أصبح الشارب محور حياتي
Every day -- this morning, I wake up and go, my life
كل يوم -- هذا الصباح ، أستيقظ وأذهب، حياتي
is about a mustache. (Laughter)
محورها الشارب ( ضحك)
Essentially, I'm a mustache farmer. (Laughter)
أساسا ، أنا مُزارع الشارب (ضحك)
And my season is November. (Applause)
وموسمي هو شهر نوفمبر ( تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So in 2005, the campaign got more momentum,
بعدها في عام 2005 ، أصبحت الحملة أكثر نشاطا ،
was more successful in Australia and then New Zealand,
أكثر نجاحا في أستراليا ثم في نيوزيلندا ،
and then in 2006 we came to a pivotal point.
وفي عام 2006 وصلنا إلى مرحلة حاسمة
It was consuming so much of our time after hours
لقد كانت الحملة تستهلك الكثير من وقتنا ، بعد ساعات
on weekends that we thought, we either need
من العمل في نهاية الأسبوع ، فقررنا بأننا بحاجة إلى إما
to close this down or figure a way to fund Movember
إنهاء الأمر أو إيجاد طريقة لتمويل موفمبر
so that I could quit my job and go and spend more time
حتى أستطيع الإستقالة من عملي و قضاء وقت أكثر
in the organization and take it to the next level.
في الجمعية حتى أصل بها إلى المرحلة التالية
It's really interesting when you try and figure a way
إنه فعلا شي ممتع محاولة إيجاد طريقة
to fund a fundraising organization
لتمويل جمعية لجمع تبرعات
built off growing mustaches. (Laughter)
مبنية على تربية الشوارب (ضحك)
Let me tell you that there's not too many people interested
دعوني أخبركم بأنه لا يوجد الكثير من الناس المهتمين
in investing in that, not even the Prostate Cancer Foundation,
بالإستثمار في مشروع كهذا، ولا حتى مؤسسة سرطان البروستات ،
who we'd raised about 1.2 million dollars for at that stage.
والتي كان بإستطاعتنا أن نجمع لها 1.2 مليون دولار في تلك المرحلة
So again we persisted, and Foster's Brewing came to the party
ولكننا ثبتنا وأصررنا ، و حضرت شركة فوسترز بروينق إحدى حفلاتنا
and gave us our first ever sponsorship,
و أصبحت أول راعِ لنا
and that was enough for me to quit my job, I did consulting on the side.
لقد كان ذلك كافيا لي كي أستقيل من عملي ،و قمت بالعمل كإستشاري كعمل جانبي
And leading into Movember 2006,
و بالوصول لموفمبر 2006،
we'd run through all the money from Foster's,
كنا قد استنفذنا كل المال الذي حصلنا عليه من شركة فوسترز
we'd run through all the money I had, and essentially
استنفذنا كل ما أملك من مال ،
we had no money left, and we'd convinced all our suppliers --
لم يعد لدينا أية نقود ، وقمنا بإقناع الموردين
creative agencies, web development agencies,
و وكالات الإبداع ، ووكالات تطوير شبكة الإنترنت ،
hosting companies, whatnot -- to delay their billing until December.
الشركات المستضيفة، -- كي يأجلوا دفع الفواتير حتى شهر ديسيمبر.
So we'd racked up at this stage about 600,000 dollars
بالتالي في تلك المرحلة كنا قد تحملناحوالي 600،000 دولار
worth of debt. So if Movember 2006 didn't happen,
كدين .بالتالي إن لم يتم موفمبر 2006 ،
the four founders, well, we would've been broke,
عندها ،نحن المؤسسين الأربعة، سنصبح مفلسين
we would've been homeless, sitting on the street
قد نصبح بلا مأوى ، متشردين في الشارع
with mustaches. (Laughter)
بشواربنا . (ضحك)
But we thought, you know what, if that's the worst thing
لكننا فكرنا ، حسنا ،إن كان هذا أسوء شيء
that happens, so what?
قد يحدث ، ماذا في ذلك ؟
We're going to have a lot of fun doing it, and it taught us
سنحصل على الكثير من المتعة بالقيام به ، ولقد علمنا
the importance of taking risks and really smart risks.
أهمية المجازفة ، المجازفة بذكاء
Then in early 2007, a really interesting thing happened.
بعدها في عام 2007، حصل أمر مشوق
We had Mo Bros from Canada, from the U.S.,
فلقد بدأ إخوة شوارب من كندا ، أمريكا
and from the U.K. emailing us and calling us and saying,
و من بريطانيا ، بمراسلتنا عبر البريد الإلكتروني والإتصال بنا قائلين :
hey, there's nothing for prostate cancer.
يا صاح ، لا يوجد شيء لسرطان البروستات .
Bring this campaign to these countries.
أحضروا هذه الحملة إلى بلادنا
So we thought, why not? Let's do it.
عندها فكرنا، لم لا ؟ لنقم بهذا
So I cold-called the CEO of Prostate Cancer Canada,
عندها قمت بمحادثة كبير الإداريين التنفيذيين لمؤسسة سرطان البروستات في كندا ،
and I said to him, "I have this most amazing concept."
وقلت له : "لدي فكرة رائعة جدا،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"It's going to transform your organization. I don't want
قد تكون بمثاية نقلة لجمعيتك ، لا أرغب
to tell you about it now, but will you meet with me
بإطلاعك عليها الآن، لكن هل تقابلني
if I fly all the way to Toronto?" So I flew here,
إن أتيت إلى تورنتو ؟" بعدها قمت بالسفر إلى كندا
met down on Front Street East, and we sat in the boardroom,
تقابلنا عند الناحية الشرقية من شارع فرونت، و جلسنا في مجلس الإدراة
and I said, "Right, here's my vision of getting men growing mustaches
و قلت :"حسنا ، هذه رؤيتي لتربية الرجال شواربهم
all across Canada raising awareness and funds for your organization."
في جميع أنحاء كندا لرفع الوعي و لجمع التبرعات لجمعيتك "
And he looked at me and laughed and said,
نظر إلي ، ضحك ، ثم قال
"Adam, sounds like a really novel idea, but we're
" آدم ،إنها حقا فكرة جديدة ، ولكننا
an ultraconservative organization." (Laughter)
جمعية متحفظة " (ضحك)
I've heard this before. I know how it goes.
لقد سمعت هذا الكلام من قبل . و أعلم كيف سينتهي
But he said, "We will partner with you,
لكنه قال: "سنصبح شركاؤك ،
but we're not going to invest in it. You need to figure
ولكننا لن نستثمر في هذا الأمر. عليك إيجاد
a way to bring this campaign across here and make it work."
طريقة لإحضار حملتك إلى هنا وإنجاحها"
So what we did was, we took some of the money that
بالتالي مافعلناه هو أننا أخذنا بعض المال الذي
we raised in Australia to bring the campaign across
كنا قد جمعناه في أستراليا لنقل الحملة إلى هنا
to this country, the U.S, and the U.K., and we did that
إلى هذه البلد ، إلى أمريكا و بريطانيا ، ولقد قمنا بذلك
because we knew, if this was successful,
لأننا علمنا بأنه إذا نجح هذا الأمر ،
we could raise infinitely more money globally
سنستطيع عالميا جمع الكثير من المال
than we could just in Australia. And that money
أكثر مما نستطيع جمعه في أستراليا . و بهذا المال
fuels research, and that research will get us to a cure.
سنمول البحوث ، وهذه البحوث ستصل إلى علاج
And we're not about finding an Australian cure
ولم نكن نسعى للحصول على علاج أسترالي
or a Canadian cure, we're about finding the cure.
أو علاج كندي ، همنا هو إيجاد علاج
So in 2007, we brought the campaign across here,
لذلك في عام 2007، أحضرنا الحملة إلى هنا
and it was, it set the stage for the campaign.
ولقد كان عرض للحملة
It wasn't as successful as we thought it would be.
لم تكن ناجحة كما توقعنا
We were sort of very gung ho with our success in Australia
فلقد كنا في قمة الحماس من مبادرتنا ونجاحها في أستراليا
and New Zealand at that stage.
و نيوزيلندا في تلك المرحلة
So that year really taught us the importance of being patient
لذا في تلك السنة تعلملنا أهمية أن نصبر
and really understanding the local market before you
و أن نفهم السوق المحلية قبل أن
become so bold as to set lofty targets.
نقدم على وضع أهداف بارزة بتغطرس
But what I'm really pleased to say is, in 2010,
لكن ما يسعدني قوله ، أنه في عام 2010
Movember became a truly global movement.
أصبح موفمبر حركة عالمية
Canada was just pipped to the post in terms of
كانت كندا مجرد قناة العبور لما بعد كونها
the number one fundraising campaign in the world.
حملة جمع التبرعات الأولى في العالم
Last year we had 450,000 Mo Bros spread across the world
حصلنا العام الماضي على 450,000 إخوان شوارب من جميع أنحاء العالم
and together we raised 77 million dollars.
وسويا جمعنا 77 مليون دولار
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And that makes Movember now the biggest funder
وهذا الأمر جعل من موفمبر الآن أكبر ممول
of prostate cancer research and support programs in the world.
لبحوث وبرامج دعم سرطان البروستات في العالم
And that is an amazing achievement when you think about
وهذا إنجاز رائع حين تفكر بكوننا
us growing mustaches. (Laughter)
نربي شواربنا ( ضحك)
And for us, we have redefined charity.
وبالنسبة لنا ، فلقد أعدنا صياغة مفهوم الجمعية الخيرية
Our ribbon is a hairy ribbon. (Laughter)
شريطنا الوسامي هو عبارة عن شريط مكسو بالشعر ( ضحك)
Our ambassadors are the Mo Bros and the Mo Sistas,
سفراءنا هم إخوة الشوارب وأخوات الشوارب
and I think that's been fundamental to our success.
و بإعتقادي هذا هو سبب نجاحنا
We hand across our brand and our campaign to those people.
لقد قمنا بتسليم علامتنا التجارية و حملتنا لهؤلاء الأشخاص
We let them embrace it and interpret it in their own way.
جعلناهم يتبنوها و يترجموها على طريقتهم
So now I live in Los Angeles, because
أعيش الآن في لوس أنجلوس ، لأنه
the Prostate Cancer Foundation of the U.S. is based there,
مقر مؤسسة سرطان البروستات الأمريكية
and I always get asked by the media down there,
ودائما ما أُسأل من قبل وسائل الإعلام هنا ،
because it's so celebrity-driven,
وذلك لأن لوس أنجلوس تتبع خطى المشاهير
"Who are your celebrity ambassadors?"
" من سفرائك من المشاهير؟"
And I say to them, "Last year we were fortunate enough
فأقول لهم ،" لقد كنا محظوظين جدا العام الماضي
to have 450,000 celebrity ambassadors."
حيث حصلنا على 450،000 سفير من المشاهير "
And they go, "What, what do you mean?"
فيستمروا " ماذا، مالذي تعنيه؟"
And it's like, everything single person, every single Mo Bro
أصبح وكأن كل شخص ، كل أخ شارب
and Mo Sista that participates in Movember
و كل أخت شارب شاركوا معنا في موفمبر
is our celebrity ambassador, and that is so, so important
هم مشاهيرنا ، وهذا مهم ، مهم جدا
and fundamental to our success.
و أمر أساسي لنجاحنا
Now what I want to share with you is
الآن ما أرغب مشاركتكم به هو
one of my most touching Movember moments,
إحدى لحظات موفمبر المؤثرة جدا
and it happened here in Toronto last year,
و لقد حصلت هنا في تورنتو العام الماضي ،
at the end of the campaign.
في نهاية الحملة
I was out with a team. It was the end of Movember.
لقد كنت بالخارج مع الفريق . كانت نهاية موفمبر .
We'd had a great campaign, and to be honest, we'd had
لقد كانت حملتنا عظيمة ، و صدقا ، كنا قد
our fair share of beer that night, but I said,
حصلنا على مايكفي من البيرة تلك الليلة، ولكنني قلت ،
"You know what, I think we've got one more bar left in us." (Laughter)
" انظروا ، أعتقد أنه لازال بإستطاعتنا الذهاب إلى البار" (ضحك)
So we piled into a taxi, and this is our taxi driver,
عندها تكدسنا في تاكسي ، وهذا سائق التاكسي
and I was sitting in the back seat, and he turned around
لقد كنت جالسا في المقعد الخلفي ، التفت سائق التاكسي إلى الوراء
and said, "Where are you going?"
وقال : " إلى أين تريدون الذهاب؟ "
And I said, "Hang on, that is an amazing mustache."
فقلت له :" لحظة ، إن هذا شارب مدهش "
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
And he said, "I'm doing it for Movember." And I said,
فقال :" أقوم بتربيته من أجل موفمبر". فقلت :
"So am I." And I said, "Tell me your Movember story."
"و أنا كذلك ". و قلت: " أخبرني عن قصتك مع موفمبر "
And he goes, "Listen, I know it's about men's health,
فقال : " اسمع ، أعلم أنه عن صحة الرجل ،
I know it's about prostate cancer, but this is for breast cancer."
أعلم أنه عن سرطان البروستات ، ولكن شاربي هذا لسرطان الثدي "
And I said, "Okay, that's interesting."
فقلت: " حسنا ، هذا شيء مشوق "
And he goes, "Last year, my mom passed away from breast cancer in Sri Lanka,
فأكمل : " في العام الماضي ، توفيت والدتي جراء سرطان الثدي في سيريلانكا ،
because we couldn't afford proper treatment for her,"
لأننا لم نستطع توفير العلاج المناسب لها "
and he said, "This mustache is my tribute to my mom."
وقال : " لذا هذا الشارب هو جزيتي لأمي "
And we sort of all choked up in the back of the taxi,
خنقتنا العبرة جميعا
and I didn't tell him who I was, because I didn't think it was appropriate,
ولم أخبره بمن أكون ، لم أعتقد أنه من اللائق
and I just shook his hand and I said, "Thank you so much.
قمت بمصافحته قائلا : " شكرا جزيلا ،
Your mom would be so proud."
أعتقد أن والدتك ستفخر بك "
And from that moment I realized that Movember
ومنذ تلك اللحظة ، فهمت بأن موفمبر
is so much more than a mustache, having a joke.
أكثر من مجرد شارب ، أكثر من مجرد مزحة
It's about each person coming to this platform,
إنه عن كل شخص يدخل هذا البرنامج
embracing it in their own way,
و يتبناه على طريقته ،
and being significant in their own life.
و يصبح أمر مهم في حياته
For us now at Movember, we really focus on
من جهتنا نحن في موفمبر ، نركز بشدة على
three program areas, and having a true impact:
ثلاثة نواحي لها تأثير عميق :
awareness and education,
الوعي ، التثقيف ،
survivor support programs, and research.
برامج لدعم الناجين من المرض و برامج لدعم البحوث
Now we always focus, naturally, on how much we raise,
حاليا نركز بالطبع على مقدار المال الذي نجمعه ،
because it's a very tangible outcome, but for me,
لأنها نتيجة ملموسة ، لكن بالنسبة لي
awareness and education is more important than the funds we raise,
التوعية والتثقيف، أهم بكثير من المال الذي جمعناه
because I know that is changing and saving lives today,
لأنني على يقين بأن التغيير و الحفاظ على حياة الناس اليوم
and it's probably best exampled by
والذي يمكن طرح أفضل مثال عليه
a young guy that I met at South by Southwest
شاب قابلته في الجنوب ،عند الجنوب الغربي
in Austin, Texas, at the start of the year.
في أوستن ، تكساس ،في بداية العام
He came up to me and said, "Thank you for starting Movember."
أتاني قائلا : " شكرا لأنك ابتدأت موفمبر "
And I said, "Thank you for doing Movember."
فقلت له " شكرا لأنك تشارك في موفمبر "
And I looked at him, and I was like, "I'm pretty sure you can't grow a mustache." (Laughter)
فنظرت إليه و قلت : " يبدو لي أنه ليس بإستطاعتك تربية شاربك " (ضحك )
And I said, "What's your Movember story?"
وقلت : " ماهي قصتك مع موفمبر ؟"
And he said, "I grew the worst mustache ever." (Laughter)
فقال : " لقد قمت بتربية أسوء شارب " (ضحك)
"But I went home for Thanksgiving dinner, and pretty quickly
" لكنني ذهبت إلى منزل أهلي لحضور عشاء عيد الشكر ، و سريعا
the conversation around the table turned to
تحولت المحادثة على طاولة العشاء إلى
what the hell was going on." (Laughter)
مالذي يجري معك ؟" (ضحك)
"And we talked -- I talked to them about Movember,
" فتحدثنا ، و أخبرتهم عن موفمبر ،
and then after that, my dad came up to me, and at the age
بعدها ، أتاني والدي وفي هذا العمر
of 26, for the first time ever, I had a conversation with my dad
26 عام ، ولأول مرة ، أتحدث مع أبي
one on one about men's health. I had a conversation
رجل لرجل عن صحة الرجال , تحدثت
with my dad about prostate cancer, and I learned
مع والدي عن سرطان البروستات ، و علمت
that my grandfather had prostate cancer
بأن جدي كان مريض بسرطان البروستات
and I was able to share with my dad that he was
ولقد كان بإستطاعتي مشاركة أبي بأنه
twice as likely to get that disease, and he didn't know that,
لديه ضعف إحتمالية المرض بسرطان البروستات ، و لم يكن يعلم ذلك
and he hadn't been getting screened for it."
ولم يكن قد خضع لفحص سرطان البروستات"
So now, that guy is getting screened for prostate cancer.
بالتالي ، قام هذا الرجل بفحص السرطان
So those conversations, getting men engaged in this,
لذا هذه المحادثات ، حث الرجال على المشاركة في هذا
at whatever age, is so critically important,
في كل الأعمار ، شيء مهم جدا
and in my view so much more important
ومن وجهة نظري فإن هذا أهم جدا
than the funds we raise.
من جمع التبرعات الذي نقوم به .
Now to the funds we raise, and research,
الآن بالتبرعات التي نجمعها وبالبحوث
and how we're redefining research.
وكيف أننا أعدنا صياغة معنى البحوث
We fund prostate cancer foundations now in 13 countries.
نقوم الآن بتمويل مؤسسات سرطان بروستات في 13 دولة
We literally fund hundreds if not thousands of institutions
نمول ، فعليا ، المئات إن لم يكن الآلاف من المنظمات
and researchers around the world, and when we looked
و مراكز البحث حول العالم ، وحين ننظر
at this more recently, we realized there's a real lack
إلى هذا مؤخرا ، ندرك بأن هناك نقص حقيقي
of collaboration going on even within institutions,
في التعاون حتى بين المؤسسات ،
let alone nationally, let alone globally, and this is not unique
محليا ، و عالميا ، و هذا ليس أمر محصور
to prostate cancer. This is cancer research the world over.
بسرطان البروستات . إنما هذه أبحاث للسرطان في جميع أنحاء العالم
And so we said, right, we'd redefined charity. We need
وكما قلنا ، حسنا ، لقد قمنا بإعادة صياغة معنى العمل الخيري . نحن الآن بحاجة إلى
to redefine the way these guys operate. How do we do that?
إعادة تعريف طريقة عمل هؤلاء الباحثين . كيف نقوم بذلك ؟
So what we did was, we created a global action plan,
لذا مافعلناه هو أننا قمنا بإنشاء خطة عمل عالمية ،
and we're taking 10 percent of what's raised in each country
ونقوم بأخذ 10% من المال الذي يجمع في كل دولة
now and putting it into a global fund, and we've got
الآن ، ونقوم بوضعه في تمويل عالمي ، ولدينا
the best prostate cancer scientific minds in the world
أفضل العلماء في مجال سرطان البروستات في العالم
that look after that fund,
الذين يبحثون عن تمويل ،
and they come together each year and identify
يقوم هؤلاء العلماء بالإجتماع مرة سنويا لتحديد
the number one priority,
الأولوية الأهم ،
and that, last year, was getting a better screening test.
وهو الأمر الذي ،في العام الماضي ، حصل على أفضل إختبار فحص.
So they identified that as a priority, and then
لذا يقومون بتحديده على أنه الأولوية الأهم ، وبعدها
they've got and recruited now 300 researchers
قاموا بالتجنيد و لديهم الآن 300 باحث
from around the world that are studying that topic,
من مختلف أنحاء العالم والذين يقومون بدراسة هذا الموضوع ،
essentially the same topic.
بشكل أساسي نفس الموضوع .
So now we're funding them to the tune of about
لذا نقوم الآن بتمويلهم إلى مايصل قيمته
five or six million dollars to collaborate
5 أو 6 مليون دولار للمساهمة
and bringing them together, and that's a unique thing
و لجمعهم سويا ، وهذا أمر فريد من نوعه
in the cancer world, and we know, through that collaboration,
في عالم السرطان ، ونحن نعلم ، من خلال هذا التعاون ،
it will accelerate outcomes.
سيتم تسريع عملية الحصول على نتائج
And that's how we're redefining the research world.
وهذه هي الطريقة التي أعدنا بها صياغة عالم البحوث
So, what I know about my Movember journey is that,
إذن ، ما أعرفه عن رحلتي مع موفمبر هي
with a really creative idea,
بواسطة فكرة فعلا مبتكرة
with passion, with persistence, and a lot of patience,
بشغف، و إصرار ، و الكثير من الصبر ،
four mates, four mustaches,
أربعة أصدقاء ، أربعة شوارب ،
can inspire a room full of people,
استطاعوا التأثير على غرفة مليئة بالناس ،
and that room full of people can go on and inspire a city,
وهذه الغرفة المليئة بالناس إستطاعت الإستمرار للتأثير على المدينة ،
and that city is Melbourne, my home.
وهذه المدينة هي ملبورن ، مدينتي
And that city can go on and inspire a state, and that state
وهذه المدينة إستطاعت الإستمرار للتأثير على ولاية ، وهذه الولاية
can go on and inspire a nation, and beyond that,
إستطاعت الإستمرار للتأثير على أمة ، و أبعد من ذلك ،
you can create a global movement
إستطاعت خلق حركة عالمية
that is changing the face of men's health.
تقوم على تغيير وجه صحة الرجل .
My name is Adam Garone, and that's my story.
اسمي آدم قيرني ، وهذه قصتي .
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا . ( تصفيق )